<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: business | Troika Tech]]></title>
  <link href="http://troikatech.com/blog/categories/business/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://troikatech.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-27T11:38:11-02:00</updated>
  <id>http://troikatech.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Vitor Capela]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[dodecaphonic@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA["REMOTE", by 37signals &mdash; &#9733;&#9733;&#9734;&#9734;&#9734;]]></title>
    <link href="http://troikatech.com/blog/2013/11/15/rework/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-15T11:52:00-02:00</updated>
    <id>http://troikatech.com/blog/2013/11/15/rework</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://37signals.com/remote/">
<img class="left <a" src="href="http://37signals.com/images/remote/remote_front.png">http://37signals.com/images/remote/remote_front.png</a>" width="400" height="600" title="&lsquo;REMOTE &ndash; by Jason Fried and DHH&rsquo;" >
</a></p>

<p>As a remote worker myself, I nodded my head frequently at the advantages and challenges presented, so the rating&rsquo;s not about a fundamental disagreement with the message or the intentions. Like the authors, I know from personal experience that commuting, facing a strict set of working hours, interruptions and living with the expectation of availability from others are some of the greatest dangers to productive work (creative work especially).</p>

<p>I did, however, expect more than short chapters and sparse data points. Maybe it&rsquo;s the programmer in me misunderstanding the whole &ldquo;business book&rdquo; thing, but perhaps the arguments would hold more weight if they were more than anedoctal. They render the whole thing as an account of what works for 37signals &mdash; a very small and relatively unknown company in the greater scheme of things. I understand that relying on managers and employers to be swayed by arguments from authority is antithetical to the book (the thesis being that remote work is a <em>rationally</em> better decision overall), but we cannot underestimate how many small-to-medium companies manage by emulation. Maybe stronger data and clearer research could counter gut reactions better.</p>

<p>I think this might be good if you need just a little push to go after this, if you&rsquo;re a bit on the fence and already considering/thinking this is a trend that should be studied and followed. If you want something to challenge your views with great insights, don&rsquo;t bother: it&rsquo;s fluffy and humane and beautifully illustrated, but you&rsquo;re probably going to leave the book mostly unchallenged.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
